<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prædictio astrologica. The great and vvonderfull prognostication, for the yeare of our Lord 1598. Written by Rodulphus Grapheus Doctor of Phisick in the Towne of Deuenter. Translated out of Dutch into English by W. P.</title>
            <author>Grapheuis, Rodulphus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17812</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 450.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114988</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850208</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850208</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15395</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17812)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15395)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1272:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prædictio astrologica. The great and vvonderfull prognostication, for the yeare of our Lord 1598. Written by Rodulphus Grapheus Doctor of Phisick in the Towne of Deuenter. Translated out of Dutch into English by W. P.</title>
                  <author>Grapheuis, Rodulphus.</author>
                  <author>Philip, W., attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by [John Windet for] Iohn Wolfe, with the assent of Rychard Watkins,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In prose and verse.</note>
                  <note>W.P. = W. Philip?--STC.</note>
                  <note>Actual printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 12189 on UMI reel 1272.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 12189.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Almanacs, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15395:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15395:1"/>
            <p>PRAEDICTIO Aſtrologica.</p>
            <p>The great and vvonderfull Prognoſtication, for the yeare of <hi>our Lord</hi> 1598.</p>
            <p>Written by Rodulphus Grapheus Doctor of Phiſick in the Towne <hi>of Deuenter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of Dutch into Engliſh by W.P</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Imprinted by Iohn Wolfe, with the aſſent of Rychard Watkins. 1598.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:15395:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15395:2"/>
            <head>Chap. 1. Of the enterance of the Sunne in the firſt point of Aries, and of the Planets that are Lordes of the yeare.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E read in the holy ſcriptures, that great kingdomes and princely Cities for their ſinnes haue beene altered and brought vnder the gouernement of ſtrange nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and that many townes for their wickedneſſe haue béene puniſhed, and brought in ſubiection: and Chriſt ſayth, that we neuer know him but when wee are viſited with ſome affliction. I find by right calculation, that this yeare of our Lorde <hi>1598.</hi> according to the meridian of the towne of <hi>Deuentre,</hi> and other places lying vnder <hi>52.</hi> degrées and <hi>40.</hi> minutes, and after the olde ſtile beginneth vpon the <hi>10.</hi> of March, and according to the new ſtile vpon the <hi>20.</hi> of March in the afternoone, a little after <hi>12.</hi> of the clocke, when the ſunne entreth into Aries, at which time it ſtandeth in the middle of the element, and then night and day through all the worlde are all of one length, and as <hi>Ouid</hi> ſaith, <hi>noua temporisaetas,</hi> then the Sunne by his heat openeth the earth, and reuiueth it, which by the cold of the Winter ſeaſon was deade and withered, making graſſe, trées, and all thinges elſe ſo fayre and gréene, that it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all creatures liuing to reioyce, and therevpon all learned men are of opinion, that this time of the year, the world heauen, and earth, and all the creatures therein were created, and many wonderfull workes of God performed therein as the deliuery of the children of Iſrael out of <hi>Aegipt,</hi> the conception of the Virgin Mary, and after that his paſſion, death, and reſurrection vpon the ſame day. I find <hi>Saturne</hi> aſcendent Eaſtwarde in the <hi>24.</hi> degrée of <hi>Sagittarius</hi> in the ſecond houſe, <hi>Iupiter</hi> in the <hi>2.</hi> degrée
<pb facs="tcp:15395:3"/>of Cancer, in the <hi>8.</hi> houſe, Mars in the <hi>4.</hi> degrée of Taurus &amp; the <hi>6.</hi> houſe, the Sunne in the firſt degrée of Aries, and the <hi>4.</hi> houſe, Venus in the thirde degrée of Aries and the <hi>4.</hi> houſe hard by the Sunne, Mercury in Piſces, the Moone in the <hi>11.</hi> degrée of Piſces, and the <hi>4.</hi> houſe, the Dragous heade in the firſt degrée of Gemini in the ſeuenth houſe, and ſo beginneth this year <hi>1598.</hi> whereby we plainely ſée, that the Moone and Mercury are Lords of the yeare, and Mars aſſiſtant, and are both founde in a wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſigne. The reſt of the planets for the moſt parte are weake and badly plac'ſt, wherevpon we muſt grounde our iudgement, and procéede accordingly, making the ſituation and coniunction of euery Planet, whereby it is found, that this ſhall bee none of the beſt yeares, for that the effects of the yeares <hi>95.96.</hi> and <hi>97.</hi> do yet continue, whereby I iudge, that this yeare many craftie and ſecreat enterpriſes will bee wrought both by water and by land, and that there is a ſpeciall matter pretended, which will be to the ouerthrow and aduancement of diuers perſons, whereby certayne prouinces ſhall bee brought into extreame miſery and deſolation, ſpecially ſuch countries as lie vnder Cancer, and her quadrangle, as <hi>Brabant, Flanders, Fraunce,</hi> and the prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces bordering vppon it. <hi>Ciprianus Leouitius</hi> ſaith touching the reuolution of this yeare, that it threatneth vs with much rayne, great ſickneſſe, and bloudy and cruell warres, as alſo that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Princes and great men both ſpirituall and temporall ſhalbe ouerthrowne and caſt in priſon, whereby much miſery and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous alterations ſhall happen among the common people: for that in this reuolution of the world the effect of two eclipſes, one of the Sunne, the other of the Moone ſhall happen. Wherefore I counſell all good Chriſtians to be watchfull, that theſe thinges come not ſodainly vppon them, and ſo I will ende this Chapter with the wordes of <hi>Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Ni Deus aedificet fruſtrà domus illa paratur,</l>
               <l>Quam volet humanus conſtituiſſe labor.<note place="margin">Pſal. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Ni Deus inuigilet, fruſtra cuſtode tuentur.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:15395:3"/>
            <head>Chap. 2. Of good and euil fortune, ſtrife &amp; contention betweene men and women, being young and louely like Venus dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges, vpon whom all the world doth caſt their eyes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or that mans nature is addicted to hear and ſée ſtrange thinges, I haue here ſet downe the ſignification of the heauenly influences of this yeare <hi>1598.</hi> which I write to giue cauſe of watchfulneſſe to careleſſe men: I find by the right calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the prouincial figure, that loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Venus,</hi> coupeled with <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Mercurie,</hi> ſignifieth good fortune to <hi>Venus</hi> children, women, yong maides, and all ſwéete <hi>Venus</hi> dearlinges, which gladly take all that is giuen them, they ſhall haue good fortune by gifts, preſentes, Iewelles, apparell, and other toyes, which if they haue not it will be great griefe vnto them. I finde the Planet <hi>Venus</hi> well placed in <hi>Aquarius,</hi> which ſignifieth great fauour to all women in generall, as well ſpiritual as temporal: women ſhall by nature flouriſh, and be loftie, they ſhall be much beloued, and diuers that are of meane parentage and degrée, ſhall by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage riſe and be preferred to high eſtate, but ſome of them muſt take care that when they are at the higheſt, that they kéep them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues at that ſtay: ſuch proude &amp; lordly women, that often ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at a ſtraw, and are ſoone troden vpon the toes, which alway ſing the vnpleaſant ſong, they ſhall cauſe great ſorrow and grief vnto their huſbands by chiding and contention, for that a woman which chideth without reaſon, doth often driue her huſbande out of dores, whereby ſhall ariſe ſtrife, hartes griefe, mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and other miſfortunes. I finde <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction. <hi>Dabit inceſtas, libidines, fornicationes, adulteria, coniunctiones virorum ac mulierum horrendas &amp; abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandas.</hi> In the laſt part of the yeare I find there will bée great deceit and vntruth among men, whom women and maides ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:15395:4"/>féede with fayre wordes, and pay them with the like, ſtanding much vpon their credites and reputations, alſo I find the Planet <hi>Venus</hi> to bee retrograde, which ſignifieth great quarrels and contentions with ſuch as men haue made of their ſecreat coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, where vpon ſhall follow griefe, ſorrow, and diuers diſeaſes. You ſhall likewiſe heare of great ſtrife betwéene men and their wiues, whereby controuerſie will ariſe, ſo that many weddinges ſhall be holden, where there wil be no muſicke, and where the Lorde or rulers of the land ſhall be betrayed. I find alſo in the prouinciall figure, that <hi>Iupiter</hi> is eleuated aboue <hi>Venus,</hi> which ſignifieth that womens nature is alwayes deſirous of pleaſure, for they are the mother of our generation: They ſhall alſo bee fortunate in childbearing, and are worthy of honour in all places. The quadrangle of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> bringeth no good tydinges to olde men, and others that vſe many women, for they ſhall bée bitten and not hurt, euery man looke to himſelfe and be careful.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. 3. Of the Eclipſes of this yeare 1598. and of wars and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and other vntrue dealings among men, which the Almightie God according to his great goodnes can change and conuert as pleaſeth him, and of the beginning &amp; end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Turkes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E are al greatly to prayſe the Lord, that he hath giuen vs the right knowledge of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomie, and made vs know the nature of Eclipſes, to ſhew <hi>cauſas, rationes &amp; demonſtrationes,</hi> and when the Sunne and Moone are eclipſed, diuers coniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the vppermoſt Planets are openly ſéene, (which neuer fayleth) as you may read in the books of anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Aſtronomers, as alſo in writings. I find that in this yeare <hi>1598.</hi> we ſhall haue thrée Eclipſes, one of the Sunne, and two of the Moone: the firſt Eclipſe of the Moone will bee ſéene here in our meridian and Pole, being vnder <hi>52.</hi> degrées and <hi>40.</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes
<pb facs="tcp:15395:4"/>in the Towne of <hi>Deuentre</hi> and other places bordering on the ſame, vpon the <hi>12.</hi> of Februarie at <hi>6.</hi> of the clocke and <hi>34.</hi> minutes in the morning, in the third degrée and <hi>3.</hi> minutes of <hi>Virgo,</hi> not farre from the Dragons tayle, and will beginne to be eclipſed at <hi>4.</hi> of the clocke and <hi>24.</hi> minutes, and in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning end at <hi>8.</hi> of the clocke <hi>14.</hi> minutes: we of <hi>Deuentre</hi> and the low countries ſhall ſée the beginning and the middle, but not the end thereof: the effect and working of this firſt Eclipſe ſhal continue a whole yeare. The ſecond Eclipſe ſhall be of the Sun, and ſhalbe ſéene vpon the <hi>25.</hi> of Februarie <hi>(Stilo antiquo)</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what before <hi>10.</hi> of the clocke, and <hi>(Stilo nouo)</hi> vppon the <hi>7.</hi> of March before <hi>10.</hi> of the clocke and <hi>48.</hi> minutes, and ſhal be <hi>8.</hi> points great, in the <hi>17.</hi> degrée and <hi>14.</hi> minutes of <hi>Piſces,</hi> not farre from the Dragons head, it ſhall beginne to darken at <hi>9.</hi> of the clocke, and <hi>50.</hi> minutes before noone, and end at <hi>11.</hi> and <hi>46</hi> minutes. This Eclipſe ſhall take effect the <hi>17.</hi> of July <hi>1598.</hi> and end the <hi>22.</hi> of Iune <hi>1600.</hi> The third Eclipſe ſhalbe of the Moone, which ſhall be ſéene vpon the <hi>6.</hi> of Auguſt, and after the new ſtile the <hi>16.</hi> of Auguſt, at <hi>7.</hi> of the clocke and <hi>35.</hi> minutes after noone: the colour thereof ſhall be blacke, mixed with ſome redde, in the <hi>23.</hi> degrée and <hi>29.</hi> minutes of <hi>Aquarius,</hi> not farre from the Dragons head, and ſhal begin to darken in the euening at <hi>5.</hi> of the clocke and <hi>51.</hi> minutes, and end the ſame euening at <hi>9.</hi> of the clocke: we of the Netherlandes ſhall not ſée the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof, but onely the middle and the end. <hi>Luna enim to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta tenebroſa ab Horzionte noſtro ortiuo emerget.</hi> This E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe ſhal take effect the <hi>24.</hi> of Auguſt <hi>(Stilo antiquo)</hi> and ende on the fift of December <hi>1598.</hi> The <hi>Arabian</hi> and <hi>Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Aſtronomers ſay, that one Eclipſe of the Sun is worſe then <hi>6.</hi> Eclipſes of the Moone, ſpecially when they happen in one month, as now they doe. <hi>Vno menſe ſubit tenebras cum Lum vterum que, Tunc gemina cauſa triſtia fata ferunt.</hi> We haue this yeare likewiſe diuers coniunctions and aſpects of Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, which ſignifie much warres, troubles, mutinies, bloodſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges, and ſecret practiſes in the low Countries, and thoſe that lie Weſt ſouthweſt from it. The countries and kingdoms that lye Eaſtward towardes the riſing of the Sunne, and vnder <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,
<pb facs="tcp:15395:5"/>Cancer, Leo</hi> and <hi>Scorpion,</hi> ſhalbe vexed with wars, blood-ſheddings, and ſecret practiſes, which are <hi>Grecia, Turkie, Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couia, Swethland, Ruſſia, Walachia,</hi> and certaine countries in the Mediterranean ſea, as <hi>Marſellus,</hi> the Prouince of <hi>Langue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doc, Gaſcony, Dauphine, Fraunce, England, Hungary, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia, Auſtria, Crabuten, Corinthia, Vianne, Seuenbergen,</hi> and ſuch as are contributary to the Turke, the people thereof ſhalbe ſpoyled, &amp; brought into great miſeries (as <hi>Leouitius</hi> ſaith) In the yeares <hi>1544. 48.</hi> and <hi>49.</hi> in which there appeared di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Eclipſes in <hi>Scorpion,</hi> the Turkes and other Chriſtians that had fallen from the fayth of Chriſt had a great ouerthrowe by the mightie king of <hi>Perſia,</hi> as Hiſtoriographers do witneſſe. Alſo the Emperours <hi>Maximilian</hi> and <hi>Rodulphus,</hi> with other mightie Princes, as <hi>Sigiſmund Bathorius</hi> in <hi>Tranſiluania,</hi> and diuers princes and Lordes that haue rebelled againſt the Turke, with other Princes and Lordes by Gods helpe for certain years haue had great fortunes and victories againſt our auncient ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my the Turke: ſo ſhall the Chriſtian princes by Gods power, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chief of al princes haue much more good fortune and aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the Turke and Sarraſens, ſo they follow it, as the olde verſe ſayth, <hi>Fronte capillata poſt eſt occaſio calua:</hi> We may ſit at a table and yet eate no meate, and ſo the good fortune that God ſendeth vs may be neglected, if wee follow it not, and for that in the yeare <hi>1584.</hi> it was the fiery Triangle, and that the Turkes Empire began in the watry Triangle, ſo his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre ſhall decay and bee ouerthrowne in the fierie Trigonis or Triangle, which decay hath begunne now within fewe yeares vnder the fiery Triangle, as in the yeares <hi>1595. 96.</hi> and <hi>97.</hi> it hath well béene ſeene, but the greateſt fall and hardeſt pinch that the kingdome of <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſhall indure, according to my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall be in the yeares <hi>1603.</hi> or <hi>1607.</hi> and then in <hi>an. 1610</hi> it ſhal be wholly ouerthrowne. Such propheſies certaine of the Turkes themſelues do write, which they do much feare, and are grieued thereat, for in the ſaid propheſies it is euidently ſaid, that the Citie of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> ſhal not continue aboue <hi>150.</hi> years in his authoritie, neyther yet their religion aboue <hi>1000.</hi> years, As alſo that there ſhal not be aboue <hi>14.</hi> Emperours of Turkey,
<pb facs="tcp:15395:5"/>that are of <hi>Ottomans</hi> race, and then it ſhall decay and be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ouerthrowne, which if it happen all Chriſtendome hath cauſe to reioyce. The Citie of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> was taken from the Chriſtians by the Turke in <hi>anno 1453.</hi> and <hi>Mahomets</hi> falſe religion began among the Turkes in <hi>an. 613.</hi> now if you adde <hi>150,</hi> to <hi>1453.</hi> which is the yeare of the winning of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> by the Turkes, and <hi>613.</hi> to <hi>1598.</hi> to ſée when it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <hi>1000.</hi> yeares for the continuance of <hi>Mahomets</hi> law, they will fall out in <hi>an. 1603.</hi> and <hi>1613.</hi> and the Turke that now is called <hi>Mahomet</hi> the thirde is the <hi>14.</hi> Emperour of the race of <hi>Ottoman,</hi> as all Hiſtories do witnes, touching that which hath béene written by <hi>Iohn Lichtenberg, Martin Snellenbergh,</hi> and ſpecially by <hi>Iohn Hilten</hi> a learned Fryer of <hi>Eiſanach,</hi> that when we ſhall write <hi>1600.</hi> the Turke by that time ſhall haue run through al <hi>Germany,</hi> but wherevpon they write if I know not, vnleſſe I be otherwiſe inſtructed: Wherewith I will end this Chapter with the wordes of <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> Lord God we beſéech thée help vs, not for that the heauens and courſe of the planets do threaten vs with many miſeries, but becauſe the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie of the Diuell at this day doth créepe and enter into all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the earth, and ſéeketh to deſtroy vs. Lorde bee mercifull vnto vs. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. 4. Of ſickneſſes and fruitfulnes of this yeare.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing conſidered the conſtitution of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>6</hi> houſe and the Lords of the ſame, from whence and from the coniunction of the Moone we make our iudgement of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, I finde <hi>Saturne</hi> to bee Lorde of the <hi>6.</hi> houſe in the Ram, which ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth new diſeaſes in the head, <hi>omnia ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera apoplexiae,</hi> cathares, paynes in the hart &amp; breaſt, laſkes, red meliſoen, burning feauers, peſtilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, agues, yellow and blacke Iandis. The yeare ſhalbe indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb facs="tcp:15395:6"/>fruitful of all kind of corne, as Rye, Barley, Wheat, Oats, Peaſe and Beans, but fruit vpon trées becauſe <hi>Venus</hi> is found to bee retrograde, ſhall indure ſome hurt, for by reaſon of the quadrangle of <hi>Mars,</hi> they ſhalbe hindred in their growth: Oyle, Hony, Hops and Flaxe ſhalbe ſcant, but Wine will be good and great plentie: The Sommer ſeaſon ſhalbe cold and moyſt with ſtrong winds, whereby Bees, Shéepe, and fruites of the earth ſhall indure much hurt: all fourefooted beaſtes ſhalbe profitable and giue good increaſe, Butter, Chéeſe and Bacon in great plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and an indifferent yeare of Acornes. There wil be no want of fruites, but rather want of amendment in men, for that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes dayly increaſeth more and more, and we giue our minds rather to beaſtly cruelties, then loue and Chriſtian humanity.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>An Aſtronomicall Diſcourſe of the particular effectes of the 12. Monethes of this <hi>yeare 1598. Written in verſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <head>Ianuarie hath <hi>31.</hi> dayes.</head>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His yeare it ſhalbe wonderfull and ſtrange,</l>
               <l>Beginning on the 10. of March to come,</l>
               <l>Wherein both Sun &amp; Moon ſhalbe eclipſt,</l>
               <l>The Sun but once, the Moon in double fold:</l>
               <l>What great effects theſe 3. Eclipſes make</l>
               <l>In time the yeare wil plainely make vs ſee,</l>
               <l>Once be you ſure no good by them will come,</l>
               <l>At the houre of ten ſomewhat before noone,</l>
               <l>The fiue and twentie day of Februarie,</l>
               <l>The Sunne ſhall be eclipſt, more then eyght points,</l>
               <l>And ſo remayne the ſpace of two long houres:</l>
               <l>The other two Eclipſes in the Moone,</l>
               <l>One about ſeuen of the clocke, and in</l>
               <l>The morning, of the ſixt of Auguſt next,</l>
               <l>Thirteene points great which cauſeth griefe abound,</l>
               <l>For diuers Planets then meete in one point,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Saturne</hi> both of nature bad,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15395:6"/>
Being conioynd preſageth vs no good,</l>
               <l>And ſeldome one miſfortune comes alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>February hath <hi>28.</hi> dayes.</head>
               <l>The firſt and laſt dayes of this preſent Month</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Mercurius</hi> are the gouernors,</l>
               <l>Whereby ſtrange thinges ſhall then be heard and ſeene,</l>
               <l>With vprores and rebellions manifolde:</l>
               <l>The common people thereby ſhall it rew,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mercurius</hi> many ſubtill ſleights ſhall vſe,</l>
               <l>But he and his in fine ſhall dearely buy it.</l>
               <l>This doth the heauens manifeſtly ſhow,</l>
               <l>In Weſterne parts ſhall be accompliſhed,</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Peters</hi> bande before the dore doth come,</l>
               <l>Or not long after to no little woe,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Mars</hi> by night his corne ſhal take in,</l>
               <l>And ſtrangely worke in couert of the ſhade,</l>
               <l>That men may not behold his actions,</l>
               <l>For many thereby might ſore moued be,</l>
               <l>What ſhall hereof enſue I will not ſay,</l>
               <l>Time will it make t'appeare in open ſight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>March hath <hi>31.</hi> dayes.</head>
               <l>In time of lent beginning of the yeare</l>
               <l>When all thinges bud and ſhew both faire and greene,</l>
               <l>Pleaſant and ſweete as time of yeare doth ſerue,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mercurius</hi> ſhall by <hi>Mars</hi> be troubled</l>
               <l>In other landes, for there ſhall come a Lord</l>
               <l>That ſodainely ſhall leape and dance for ioy,</l>
               <l>And now the force of <hi>Mars</hi> being decaide,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sol</hi> entereth, and with heate and vertue rare,</l>
               <l>And like a bryde beginneth for to raigne,</l>
               <l>Whereby this yeare ſhall be moſt flouriſhing,</l>
               <l>With more increaſe then had the yeare before,</l>
               <l>Which will bee cauſe of loue and peace likewiſe,</l>
               <l>But at the firſt it ſhall not take effect:</l>
               <l>Aſke <hi>Saint Gregory</hi> the moſt holy man,</l>
               <l>When that the Sunne beginnes in force to be,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15395:7"/>
The Planets <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> and good <hi>Iupiter</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wil vs ſupport, God ſend our cuntry peace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Aprill hath <hi>30.</hi> dayes.</head>
               <l>It is a thing that commonly is ſeene,</l>
               <l>Both in great Realmes and little prouinces,</l>
               <l>That ſtrange effects are wrought in euery place,</l>
               <l>As France ſhal make it plaine vnto our view,</l>
               <l>There ſhal the cocke gainſt nature bring forth egs</l>
               <l>And Hen like cocke ſhall crow and that full high,</l>
               <l>Which husbandman ſmall profit will procure:</l>
               <l>For he that badly hath a time to ſow,</l>
               <l>Shall find but ſmall increaſe for him to mow,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Saint Denis</hi> he ſhall turne and ſo rebell,</l>
               <l>Whereby great miſchiefe will thereof enſue,</l>
               <l>Gainſt right and ancient ſtatutes of the land,</l>
               <l>And in the end will cauſe a ſpring of hate,</l>
               <l>To flow vp and increaſe in noble harts,</l>
               <l>Which likewiſe ſhall our land make deſolate,</l>
               <l>By flattery which ſlily ſhall creepe in.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>May hath <hi>31.</hi> dayes.</head>
               <l>Walke ioyfully in the field in <hi>May,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Paſſe time away by making garlands ſweete</l>
               <l>Of fragrant flowers and Lillies that are fayre,</l>
               <l>Be bold I ſay to ſport your ſelues with ioy,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> he is gone to <hi>France</hi> here it is cold,</l>
               <l>Lillies are here ſo ſoone not to be had,</l>
               <l>Keep wel your holds, your ſconces watch &amp; ward</l>
               <l>Borrow new ſummes vpon the quittance olde,</l>
               <l>Make alliance, but yet with good foreſight,</l>
               <l>Leaue of to mourne &amp; ſigh, it is not good.</l>
               <l>That which full ſtout did ſtand ſhal haue a fall,</l>
               <l>He that was proude in all his actions,</l>
               <l>And among beaſts accounted fierce and ſtrong,</l>
               <l>Shall become weake in that he takes in hand,</l>
               <l>And too much luſt ſhall make him impotent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:15395:7"/>
               <head>Iune hath <hi>30.</hi> dayes.</head>
               <l>Looke out to Sea, watch and you ſhall behold,</l>
               <l>Great ſtore of ſhippes ſayling in companies,</l>
               <l>The riches of God Neptune to defende,</l>
               <l>But wordes ſhal cauſe a noyſe and tumults ſtrange</l>
               <l>The noiſe of Phifes and Drums ſhal ſound ful high</l>
               <l>Ships you ſhal ſee to winde and twine each way,</l>
               <l>Where ſhot and powder ſhal not ſpared be;</l>
               <l>That ſhall not fayle, men may it not neglect,</l>
               <l>Much blood it ſhal cauſe to be ſpilt in vayne,</l>
               <l>Yet little profite ſhall it breed thereby</l>
               <l>To common people, which are not eſteemde,</l>
               <l>Many a man ſhall fall into miſhappe</l>
               <l>That liu'd in peace and had the worlde at wil:</l>
               <l>Aske good <hi>S. Iohn</hi> he ſhal you wonders tell,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Mary Magdaline</hi> ſhal weepe ful ſore,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>S. Iacob</hi> will at large ſhew what it meanes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Iuly hath <hi>31.</hi> dayes.</head>
               <l>As we this month do thoroughly behold,</l>
               <l>And books peruſe that ſpeake of wonders ſtrange,</l>
               <l>And likewiſe men be mindful and take care,</l>
               <l>In euery place to looke vnto our ſelues,</l>
               <l>Then we may ſay and proue it to be true,</l>
               <l>That in this month many ſhal weep and waile,</l>
               <l>Such as do vnder <hi>Cancer</hi> ſtill remayne,</l>
               <l>Hoping by anker hold ſtill to be ſafe,</l>
               <l>VVith ditch and ſluce from water you defend,</l>
               <l>You that vpon the water dwell and build,</l>
               <l>Looke well vnto your ſelues, and take good heed,</l>
               <l>That it deceyue you not vnto your coſt,</l>
               <l>On land great matters ſhalbe practiſed,</l>
               <l>If they ſhould chance to loſe their ſleeue it is no harme</l>
               <l>So that the arme from body be not cut,</l>
               <l>And though they ſhould be hindred by the cold</l>
               <l>Yet will they paſſe, God ſpeed them on their way</l>
               <l>If ſhoe be loſt, the foote it will not fayle.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:15395:8"/>
               <head>Auguſt hath <hi>31.</hi> dayes.</head>
               <l>This Month hath an Eclipſe, but to no good,</l>
               <l>Which is the ſecond of this years hard chance,</l>
               <l>Three darke Eclipſes cauſes are of woe,</l>
               <l>And torments great, that manifold ſhall be,</l>
               <l>For ſure I thinke that all euill aſpects</l>
               <l>And Planets badde that in the ſkyes are plac'd,</l>
               <l>With ſignes of wo haue banded all in one,</l>
               <l>To worke diſpight to humane creatures,</l>
               <l>A league ſhall be agreede by wicked men,</l>
               <l>Euen to the ſpoyle of their next neighbours houſe,</l>
               <l>By fighting, ſtrife, contention and debate,</l>
               <l>To ouerthrow the poore and innocent.</l>
               <l>If you behold the Equinoctiall line,</l>
               <l>And marke how the eclipſed figures ſtand,</l>
               <l>You may deuine an enterpryſe in hand,</l>
               <l>To ouerthrow the land that lyeth ſouthweſt,</l>
               <l>Betweene ſome men accord there ſhall be made,</l>
               <l>Whereby in fine a peace it will enſue:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>September hath <hi>30.</hi> dayes</head>
               <l>Agree in one moſt Chriſtian Princes braue</l>
               <l>By God ordaind your Countries to defend,</l>
               <l>That Turke preuayle not gainſt vs with his power,</l>
               <l>And Chriſtian blood be ſhed by tyrants vile,</l>
               <l>Stand vp and fight for our moſt holy faith,</l>
               <l>Which we do hope will be vnto our ioy,</l>
               <l>For in the Eaſt the infidels will ſtirre,</l>
               <l>That onely ſeeke to rob, ſpoyle, and deſtroy:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Fraunce</hi> ſhall likewiſe haue a change,</l>
               <l>And ſo dainely by meanes of ſome great charge,</l>
               <l>The one ſhall firſt vpon the other fall,</l>
               <l>Which will fall out but hardly for them both,</l>
               <l>Full many townes that on the Roane do lie,</l>
               <l>Shall by deceit be brought vnto decay:</l>
               <l>Contention ſhall abound, but in Sauoy</l>
               <l>It ſhall proceed vnto moſt bloody end:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15395:8"/>
                  <hi>Saint Mathew</hi> ſhal full many ſeperate,</l>
               <l>Which ſhalbe led like ſheep for to be ſlain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>October hath <hi>31.</hi> dayes.</head>
               <l>The rage of <hi>Mars</hi> ſhall now ſtill more abounde,</l>
               <l>Mammon ſhall ſtirre moſt vile rebellion,</l>
               <l>Whereby full ſoone many ſhal weepe and wayle,</l>
               <l>And countries ſtrange ſhall torments great indure,</l>
               <l>The ſubiect poore, ſhal onely beare the ſmart,</l>
               <l>For that deceite ſhal ketch them in her ſnare,</l>
               <l>By meanes of <hi>Mars</hi> his ſubtill practiſes,</l>
               <l>He ſhal ſpeake fayre but onely with the mouth,</l>
               <l>But ſecretly his hart is ſet on blood,</l>
               <l>Which many ſeeke, like vnto thirſtie houndes,</l>
               <l>Beware poore people what ye vndertake:</l>
               <l>It were much better, though vnto our ſhame,</l>
               <l>Our mindes were ſet on quietneſſe and peace,</l>
               <l>But now the worlde and her inhabitants,</l>
               <l>Is fild with pride, deceite and wickedneſſe,</l>
               <l>For which the Lord as angry doth vs ſcourge</l>
               <l>With bloody wars within our natiue land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Nouember hath <hi>30.</hi> dayes.</head>
               <l>I haue in other places ſignified,</l>
               <l>That children vnder <hi>Iupiter</hi> his power,</l>
               <l>Shal in the eyght houſe of the heauenly ſpheare,</l>
               <l>By euill aſpect much paine and wo indure,</l>
               <l>Which at this time accompliſhed ſhall be:</l>
               <l>Beware you Lords and gouernors ech one,</l>
               <l>Looke to your ſelues, and ſeeme not to neglect,</l>
               <l>Leaſt that the burthen heauily do fall,</l>
               <l>And ſo diſpearſe you by diſvnion,</l>
               <l>For that great blame vpon you will ariſe,</l>
               <l>It is moſt true, and therefore looke vnto it,</l>
               <l>And for your wicked life ſhal ſo fall out,</l>
               <l>The great oppreſſion of the Goſpel pure,</l>
               <l>The ſtrange iniuſtice vnto euery man</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15395:9"/>
Are ſinnes of yours, for which God doth vs plague,</l>
               <l>And layes his croſſe vpon vs euery day,</l>
               <l>For that our workes are wholly wickedneſſe:</l>
               <l>If we conuert God will withdraw his wrath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>December hath <hi>31.</hi> dayes.</head>
               <l>By placing of the figures we may ſee,</l>
               <l>And courſe of planets giue vs t'vnderſtand</l>
               <l>Howe that this ſtrife falling moſt heauily,</l>
               <l>Shall ſtill endure, although it ſeem all done,</l>
               <l>And from this place in other countries ſlide,</l>
               <l>Which likewiſe may procure them double woe,</l>
               <l>And though within this month it fall not out,</l>
               <l>Yet time will make it euidently ſeene,</l>
               <l>Therefore I neede not much thereof to ſay,</l>
               <l>On Planets can I not ſo ſurely binde,</l>
               <l>Although full many thinges they do foreſhew,</l>
               <l>For God that guideth all things by his power,</l>
               <l>(As often I haue ſaid, and find it true,</l>
               <l>What euer Planets threaten to befall)</l>
               <l>Can at his will conuert and make them voide.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15395:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
